Guide to the Brady Gallery collection, 1860-1980 RG0146
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Brady Gallery records
circa 1800 - circa 2015
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0146
7 Linear Feet
This collection contains photographs, silhouettes, drawings, paintings, diplomas, and programs associated with people and places relevant to the University. The collection also holds exhibit publications, CDs, and ephemera related to the work of the Luther W. Brady Art Gallery. The materials date from approximately 1800 to approximately 2015.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: Photographs, Architectural Drawings, Publications, Audiovisual Materials, and Objects & Ephemera. Oversize items are housed in map case drawers, and standard size items are in Boxes 1-7. Within the boxes, items are sorted by original order.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains photographs, silhouettes, drawings, paintings, diplomas, programs, exhibit publications, CDs, and ephemera. The materials date from approximately 1800 to approximately 2015. The records document students, faculty, staff, trustees, and campus buildings, as well as the work and exhibitions of the Luther W. Brady Art Gallery.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Luther W. Brady Art Gallery, 11/6/2013 [2013.038] Later additions added in 2019 and 2021.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Some audiovisual materials in Series 4 may be inaccessible.
Separated Materials
Two images: graduating classes of 1868 and 1869 were removed from the collection due to excessive damage. Both images did provide identification of the people in the images. From original archival object: Class of 1868: Names printed on mat: Mortimer Clarke, Leonidas Crendiropuls, John T. Beckley, James Pollard, Charles E. Samson, Lingham B. Allen, Joseph E. Martin, Joseph H. France, Rev. George W. Samson, D.D., LL.D. (President), Sidney W. Handy, Francis C. Bowen, William V. Bouic Jr.
Class of 1869 Names printed on mat: (back row): George Y. Coffin, Samuel S. Pleasants, Francis R. Boston, Zachariah T. Sowers, Lester F. Ward, Alexander T. Stuart, Fabian Franklin (front row): William H. Finckle, Franklin H. Kerfoot, John W. Bidgood, Rev. George W. Samson, D.D., LL.D. (President), Edward O. Leech, Edward C. Carrington, Jr.
Biographical / Historical
The Luther W. Brady Art Gallery, an educational gallery located on the second floor of the Media and Public Affairs Building, is the professional showcase for art at George Washington University. Opened in March of 2001, the Brady gallery features six to eight exhibitions each year and include University-related shows and Permanent Collection exhibitions with a focus on the Washington area. The gallery also administers the University's Permanent Collection, which includes paintings, sculptures, graphics, textiles, ceramics, historic furnishings, and photographs.
Photography; Art; Columbian College; Exhibitions; Artists
- GWU Permanent Collection-Photographs, circa 1800- circa 1948; RG0146 Series 1; 66 folder(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photographs of university-affiliated persons (students, staff, faculty, trustees). The material dates from about 1800 to about 1948.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by original order.
  - Dr. Otis Tufton Mason, 1905; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    General
    Back of photograph mat implies that the photograph was obtained by Mrs. Daniel Kerfoot Shute. It reads:
    Shute Oct. 12, 1905
    Doctor & Mrs. Shute Mrs. D. K. Shute 1719 De Sales Frame 50 47 Mat 15 65 Chq Fit 10 75 1460
  - Charles Edward Munroe, circa 1919; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Printed on Mat:
    Charles Edward Munroe Professor of Chemistry (1892-1919) Dean of the School of Graduate Studies (1893-1919) Professor Emeritus of Chemistry (1919)
  - William R. Vance, circa 1910; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Major James Carroll, 1901; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 4)
    Written on back of mat:
    Maj. James Carroll Member of the U.S. Army Yellow Fever Commission Photograph taken in 1901, Copied Oct. 1910 by H.A. Utter Plate no 71.u. sect 15 at The A.M.M.
  - Admiral Stockton, circa 1918; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rev. James McBride Starratt, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Herman Schoenfeld, circa 1926; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sterling Ruffin, circa 1928; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Printed on mat: STERLING RUFFIN Demonstrator in Anatomy (1890-1892) Professor of Medical Jurisprudence (1892-1899) Professor of Medicine (1899-1924) Professor Emeritus of Medicine (1924)
    Signed: July 12, 1928
  - Reverend George Whitefield Samson, circa 1871; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Label on photograph reads:
    REV. GEORGE WHITEFIELD SAMSON, A.B., D.D., LL.D President, Columbian College 1859-71 now The George Washington University
    Presented by Henry W. Samson
  - Buckner Magill Randolph, circa 1931; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Printed on mat:
    BUCKNER MAGILL RANDOLPH Instructor in Materia Medica (1905-1909) Professor of Materia Medica ( 1909-1923) Professor of Clinical Medicine (1923-1930) Director of Clinics (1923-1930) Professor Emeritus of Clinical Medicine (1930)
    Signed: May 25, 1931
  - T.N. McLaughlin, circa 1921; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Thomas Notley McLaughlin
    Photograph from The National Cyclopedia of American Biography
  - William Bruce King, circa 1930; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Signed: Yours very truly, William Bruce King
  - W.W. Kerr, M.D., undated; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 13)
  - Unidentifiable man, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Note attached: probably Avery Andrews, trustee (1929-1950), grad of law school
  - Unknown Portrait by Harris & Ewing, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Wendell Phillip Stafford, circa 1929; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    WENDELL PHILLIP STAFFORD Professor of Law (1907-1929) Professor Emeritus of Law (1929)
    Copyright by: Harris & Ewing
  - Daniel Kerfoot Shute, circa 1916; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    DANIEL KERFOOT SHUTE Lecturer in Anatomy (1884-1888) Professor of Anatomy (1888-1912) Professor of Ophthalmology (1912-1916) Professor Emeritus of Clinical Ophthalmology (1916)
  - Charles Williamson Richardson, circa 1929; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    CHARLES WILLIAMSON RICHARDSON Professor of Laryngology and Otology (1892-1924) Professor Emeritus of Laryngology and Otology (1924-1929)
    Signed: Sincerely, Charles W. Richardson
  - Judge Stanton J. Peele, circa 1909; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - George Perkins Merrill, circa 1929; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    GEORGE PERKINS MERRILL Professor of Geology (1892-1916) Professor Emeritus of Geology (1916-1929)
    Signed: George P. Merrill
  - Charles Corby - Trustee, circa 1925; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Charles Gerstenberg, circa 1948; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - John Bell Larner (?), circa 1930; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Huron Willis Lawson, circa 1932; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    HURON WILLIS LAWSON Assistant Professor of Pathology (1903-1909) Professor of Histology (1909-1912) Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology (1912-1932) Professor Emeritus of Obstetrics and Gynecology (1932)
  - William Kennedy Butler, circa 1917; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    WILLIAM KENNEDY BUTLER Demonstrator and Lecturer in Anatomy and Surgery (1886-1887) Professor of Ophthalmology (1900-1916) Professor Emeritus of Opthalmology (1917)
    Signed: William K. Butler
  - Charles Noble Gregory, circa 1914; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Signed:
    With Kind Remembrance, Charles Noble Gregory
  - William Miller Collier, circa 1921; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    With best wishes for the Officers and Staff of the University Treasury, and for all its students and patrons. Wm. Miller Collier Prest. "G.W.U." April 9th, 1921
  - James Howard Gore, circa 1909; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    JAMES HOWARD GORE Lecturer and Assistant Professor of Mathematics (1878-1883) Professor of Mathematics (1883-1909) Professor Emeritus of Mathematics (1909)
  - Charles Clinton Swisher, circa 1927; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    CHARLES CLINTON SWISHER Professor of History (1896-1927) Professor Emeritus of History (1927)
  - Arthur Jennings Mandy, circa 1935; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Printed on photograph:
    Arthur Jennings Mandy President Smith-Reed-Russel Society 1934-35
  - Honorable Benjamin Butterworth, circa 1897; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 31)
  - 1903 graduating class of the National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 32)
    Names of graduates printed on mat:
    back row: T.E. GIBB, W.E. BOYER, L.B. CASTELL, W.A. BRIGGS, H.A. CANDEE, H.E. HARVEY middle row: B.F. SHOWALTER, W.J. McNAMEE, FRANCES P. HUTCHINSON, L.H. LAMB, W.F. WORK, W.A. MESS, H.C. LEHMAN
    Identified professors in front row: PROF. FRED A. HOLTON, PROF. Wm. F. HILLEBRAND, PROF. SAM'L. WAGGAMAN, PROF. WYMOND H. BRADBURY, and 2 unidentified on right
  - 1891 graduating class of the National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 33)
    Names printed on mat:
    (back row): Alfred H. Wells, Chas. MacGregor, Edward F. Albert (middle row): Frank C. Haines, Henry J. Herr, Albert J. Cox, Robt. C. Williams, John W. Jennings, Gilpin Willson, Albert T. Bronaugh, Wm. J. Ryder, William G. Roe (front row): Frank V. Johnson, J. Edw'd Carroll, Chas. B. Campbell, Chas. E. Baldwin, Albert B. Hyatt, Harry D. Hutton, Chas. Scherer, James Win Harper
  - 1903 graduates of Law School, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 34)
    J. FRANCIS Jr., D.G. COWHICK, C.T. MILANS, G.H. DAVIS, R.D. RITTENOUR, E.D. ANDERSON, L.J. BAILEY, B.A. LEWIS, E.R. WHITE, W.S. PENFIELD, J. BREWER, J.R. BOREING, C.V. GRUNWELL, J.A. KUCK Jr., L.C. WILSON, D.E. STEPHAN, F.S. WHITCOMB, C.H. CORYELL, A.C. KELLOGG, G. HOLSOPPLE, L.C. MANSON, E.M. SABIN, W.G. RANDALL, F.W. SYLVESTER, JOSE HERIA
  - Unidentifiable group of 8 men, undated; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 35)
  - Class of 1902 National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 36)
    CLASS of 1902 (back row): H. Kasper Kirby, Manley J. Clark, John F. Butler, Preston C. Day, Howard M. Bradbury, Malcom G. Gibbs (front row): Lawrence P. Nolan, Prof. Wm. F. Hillebrand, Prof. Sam'l. Waggaman, Prof. Fred A. Holton, Prof. Wymond H. Bradbury
  - Unidentifiable group of 21 men, undated; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 37)
  - Class of 1896 School of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 38)
    (back row): Langdon S. Day (V. Pres.), George Latterner, Daniel F. Slattery, C. Howle Young (3rd row): Charles G. Sanders, Jugh M. Adams, John T. Murphy (Treas.), Marion E. Bullock, Alonzo J. Budenbom, W. Calhoun Furr, Arthur L. Orrison (Secy.) 2nd row): H.L. Gould, Victor H. Esch, Harry T. Dodge, H.P. Baker, Miss Jennie T. Rugg, Oden R. Sudler, Marcellus R. Wooldridge (front row): Harry M. Price, Wm. F. Hillebrand (Prof. of Chemistry & Physics), Frederick A. Holton (Prof. of Analytical Chemistry), Samuel Waggaman (Prof. of Materia Medica & Toxicology), Wymond H. Bradbury (Professor of Pharmacy), Charles B. Campbell (Asst. Prof. of Pharmacy), Charles W. Little (Pres.)
  - Columbian University, Some New Lawyers, Class of '95, 1895; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 39)
    Photographs with name and state of each 1895 Law School graduate (86 total). Also includes Law Faculty (12 total).
  - Class of 1908 National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 40)
    E.K. Richardson, Miss M.H. Richardson, M.C. Thompson, T.O. Timberlake, M.A. Pozen (Secy.), H.B. Floyd (Pres.), R.B. Thibadeau, W.D.A. Thorn, R.B. Spencer (V. Pres.), C.G. Deming, E.H. Steele, W.R. Boyer, G.H. Schulze, Jr.
  - Unidentifiable group of 17 men, undated; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 41)
  - Class of 1898 School of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 42)
    (back row): Chas. I. Griffith, L.D. Taylor, Issac Scott, S.D. Moore, F.C. Purdum, P.C. King, F.R. Richardson, C.A. McAvoy, Kirk Holmes, E.L. Mason (front row): E.A. Duckett, W.H. Bradbury, F.A. Holton, Lucretia B. Lacy, Sam'l Waggaman, M.E. Bullock, A.J. Sheridan, B.R. Franklin
  - Unidentifiable group of men and women, undated; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 43)
  - Class of 1913 National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 44)
    E.G. Swann, D.L. Maxwell (Secretary-Treasurer), W.H. Whittlesey (President), C.W. Barker (Vice President), I.A. Tennyson, Raymond Kinsey, Anna E. Mix, L.B. Whitley, R.V. Chamblin
  - Class of 1900 National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 45)
    J. Willard McChesney (D.C.), DeHaven Sharp (D.C.), S. Mason Wagner (W.Va.), Herbert W. Poole (Va.), Florence Virginia Hoskins (D.C.), H. McCoy Walters (Ill.), Charles Garrels (Ill.), Ernest Parsons (D.C.), John M. Minick (Pa.), Samuel P. Rickards (Pa.)
  - Judges of the Court of Appeals 1890, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 46)
    Signatures on mat:
    Oliver Wendell Holmes, Willis VanDevanter, John M. Harlan, Horace H. Lurton, E.D. White, Charles E. Hughes, Joseph McKenna, J.R. Lamar, William R. Day
  - Court of Appeals State of New York, circa 1883-circa 1887; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 47)
    Names printed on photo:
    Theodore Miller, Charles A. Rapallo, George F. Danforth, Chief Judge William C. Ruger, Francis M. Finch Charles Andrews, Robert Earl
  - Judges of the Court of Appeals, 1890, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 48)
    Francis M. Finch, John Clinton Gray, Charles Andrews, William C. Ruger (Chief), Robert Earl, Denis O'Brien, Rufus W. Peckham
  - George Washington Law Alumni Dinner, 1939 March 18; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 49)
    Mayflower Hotel - March 18, 1939 (Tenschert Photo)
  - Class of 1899 National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 50)
    Mat partially removed. Names printed on remainer of mat:
    Geo. D. Kehoe, Paul L. Joachim, Chas. J. Fuhrmarun (President), Timothy T. Lane (V. Pres.),Prof. Fred A. Holton, John S. Gallagher
  - Presentation to Commissioners of Federal Trade Commission of Silver Anniversary Commemorative Volume of the George Washington Law Review, 1940; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Class of 1890 National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 52)
    (back row): J.V. Yates, C.B. Heizer, W.S. Ferris, M. Waters (middle row): P.G. McComas, C.D. Owens, Chas. Earl, R.C. Dickenson, B. Ogle Tayloe, J.L. Allen, W.R. Shaw, M. Donnelly, R.V. Houston (front row): M.H. Price, D.J. Tennant, R.L. Quigley, Prof. Wm. Hallock, Prof. Sam'l Waggaman, Prof. H.E. Kalusowski, Prof. Sam'l L. Hilton, W.B. Raub, M. Griffith
  - Law Faculty, Old Law School McPherson Square, circa 1920-circa 1925; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Law Class of 1908, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Judge Advocate General Corp., circa 1919; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    (back row): Lt. Col. W.C. Clephane (George Washington Univ.), Maj. F.C. Woodward, J.A. (Univ. of Chicago), Maj. J.P. Hall, J.A. (Univ. of Chicago), Lt. Col. C.C. Tucker, J.A. (National University), Lt. Col. R.W. Miller, J.A. (Northwestern Univ.) (front row): Lt. Col. E.M. Morgan, J.A. (Yale University), Col. Eugene Wambaugh, J.A. (Harvard University), Col. J.H. Wigmore, J.A. (Northwestern Univ.), Lt. col. E.R. Keedy, J.A. (Univ. of Pennsylvania)
  - Senior Class of '91 Columbian Law School, 1891; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 58)
  - Class of 1926 College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    H.E. Baker, Dr. Kalusowski, W.L. Keller, B.A. Pettitt
  - Class of 1925 College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 60)
    Milton F. Warren, Harold C. Kinner, Faud A. Ghani, Arthur McMurray, (Dean) Henry E. Kalusowski, Henry D. Treiger
  - Faculty and Class of 1893 National College of Pharmacy, Series 1 (Oversize-folder 61)
    W.H. Bradbury, D.D. Mulcahy, H.R. Garland, F.C. Wilson, W.E. Halloran, G.J. Geiger, W.S. Udall, H. Budenbom Jr., Prof. Sam'l Waggaman, A.C. Fitch, Prof. H.F. Kalusowski, Prof. F.A. Holton, Prof. W.F. Hillebrand
  - Moot Court Old Law School - McPherson Square, circa 1921-circa 1924; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Old Law Library at McPherson Square, circa 1921-circa 1924; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - View of Columbian College About 1860-1865, circa 1860-circa 1865; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Aerial View of George Washington University, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Law Lecture Room in Old Law School Building - McPherson Square, circa 1921-circa 1924; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Silhouette of President William Staughton, c. 1800; RG0146 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Silhouette of Stephen Chapin, 1802; RG0146 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Invitation to the Reinterment Ceremony of John Howard Payne, 1883 June 9; RG0146 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Eleanor S. Washington Howard and a Sketch of the Washington Family in her Hand Writing, undated; RG0146 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- GWU Permanent Collection-Architectural drawings and paintings, circa 1970 - circa 1988; RG0146 Series 2; 9 folder(s)
  This series contains 9 architectural drawings/paintings of various campus buildings. The material dates from about 1970 to about 1988.
  - The George Washington University Office Building, undated; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 67)
    19th Street and Pennsylvania Ave.
    Mills, Petticord and Mills - Architects and Engineers
  - The George Washington University Office Building at 2123 Eye Street, NW, undated; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 68)
  - Harry F. Duncan Pavilion - The George Washington University Hospital, circa 1977; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 69)
  - GWU Campus Building, undated; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 70)
    Architects: Cooke Brackett
  - University Library, circa 1970; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 71)
  - Parking Structure at NW Corner of 22nd and H Streets, NW, undated; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 72)
  - Basic Sciences Building - The George Washington University Medical Center, undated; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 73)
  - The George Washington University Medical Center, circa 1988; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 74)
    Addition to H.B. Burns Memorial Building - Ambulatory Care Center
    Cannon/Faulkner - Architects/Engineers
  - Office Building for the George Washington University, undated; Series 2 (Oversize-folder 75)
    21st and Pennsylvania Avenue, NW
    Mills, Petticord and Mills Hellmuth, Obata & Kassabaum, Inc. Associated Architects and Engineers Washington, D.C. - St. Louis, MO
- Publications, 2006-2013; RG0146 Series 3
  This series contains exhibit publications dating from 2006-2013.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Exhibit Publications, 2006-2012; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit Publications, 2002-2013; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1990-2015; RG0146 Series 4
  Materials in this series include CDs containing information, photographs, and videos of various components of the Brady Galley's work. There are CDs that deal with adminitrative matters, such as artist bios and loan documents. There are also CDs related to exhibitions, such as "Richard Avedon: Portraits of Power" in 2009 and "Sargent and the Sea" in 2009. And, some CDs provide information about events, such as the New Student Reception and Grad Open House.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The CDs in this series may be inaccessible. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
  - CDs, 1990-2015; RG0146 (Box 6, Box 7)
    Materials include CDs containing information, photographs, and videos of various components of the Brady Galley's work. There are CDs that deal with administrative matters, such as artist bios and loan documents. There are also CDs related to exhibitions, such as "Richard Avedon: Portraits of Power" in 2009 and "Sargent and the Sea" in 2009. And, some CDs provide information about events, such as the New Student Reception and Grad Open House.
- Objects & Ephemera, 1800-2000; RG0146 Series 5
  Materials in this series include objects and ephemera from the Brady Gallery, such as diplomas, programs, and glasses. The materials range in date from about 1800 to about 2000
  - Prospectus of the Columbian College Preparatory School, 1883-1884; RG0146 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Programs of Commencement Exercises, 1825-1880; RG0146 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Order of the Hippo Glasses, undated; RG0146 (Box 5)
  - Diploma of Johannum A. Nash, undated; RG0146 (Oversize-folder 76)
  - Diploma of William Smallwood, 1825; RG0146 (Oversize-folder 77)
  - Photograph of Academic Center (Phillips Hall, Rome Hall, & Smith Hall of Art), undated; RG0146 (Oversize-folder 78)